{"tossups": [{"question": "When applied to an entire country, this process is known as an \"interdict,\" which was notably used against England under King John. This process was applied to Holy Roman Emperor Henry IV, who had to kneel in the snow at Canossa to have it reversed by Pope Gregory VII. For 10 points, identify this process of withholding sacraments from a person who has offended Catholic law.", "answer": "<b><u>excommunication</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Albert Gallatin attempted to calm the Mingo Creek Association during this event, which was suppressed by the \"Watermelon Army\" led by Light Horse Harry Lee. Sitting President George Washington personally rode out against this event in 1794. For 10 points, name this Western Pennsylvania uprising against a new excise tax on liquor.", "answer": "<b><u>Whiskey Rebellion</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A painting by this man was ordered defaced by the Council of Trent, leading to the man who altered his work being known as \"The Breeches-Painter.\" Daniele da Volterra added loincloths to cover the nudity in this man's <em>The Last Judgment</em>. For 10 points, name this painter who worked lying on his back on a scaffold to decorate the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.", "answer": "<b><u>Michelangelo</u></b> [or Michelangelo di Lodovico <b><u>Buonarroti</u></b> Simoni]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An attempt to fly this country's flag at an American school here led to the \"Martyrs' Day\" riot. This country's dictator Omar Torrijos (toh-REE-hoce) signed a treaty with Jimmy Carter that gave this country control over a formerly extraterritorial \"zone.\" For 10 points, name this country which the U.S. encouraged to declare independence from Colombia in order to build a canal.", "answer": "<b><u>Panama</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "George Taylor opened a mill to produce this good in a way that satisfied Quakers affiliated with the Free Produce Movement. Slaves in tobacco fields dreaded being \"sold down the river\" to work with this good. For 10 points, name this good produced in the Deep South, which became economically feasible again after Eli Whitney invented its \"gin.\"", "answer": "<b><u>cotton</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state was where Teddy Roosevelt once suffered an economic setback as a rancher, though today it\u2019s the site of Theodore Roosevelt National Park. This state\u2019s economy has recently boomed due to lucrative oil wells around its city of Williston. For 10 points, name this state whose capital was named to attract German immigrants, and which was depicted in the 1990\u2019s film <em>Fargo.</em>", "answer": "<b><u>North Dakota</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Near the end of this decade, the Mayerling scandal erupted. During this decade, Chinese Gordon was killed fighting the Mahdi in Sudan. The rules for colonialism were set out at the Berlin Conference during this decade. For 10 points, identify this decade in which Queen Victoria celebrated the Golden Jubilee of her 1837 accession to the throne.", "answer": "<b><u>1880</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man secured recognition of independence at the Treaty of Lausanne, which ended the deportation of his country's Greek minority. This founder of the Republican People's Party banned the wearing of fezzes and introduced the Latin alphabet as part of the \"Six Arrows\" platform. For 10 points, name this founder of modern secular Turkey.", "answer": "Mustafa <b><u>Kemal</u></b> [or Mustafa Kemal <b><u>Ataturk</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This author fictionalized Vice-President Aaron Burr in her novel <em>The Minister's Wooing</em> and depicted fugitives in the Great Dismal Swamp in <em>Dred</em>. She wrote a \"key to\" her major novel, which led Abraham Lincoln to describe her as \"the little lady who started this big war.\" For 10 points, name this author who created Simon Legree in the anti-slavery book <em>Uncle Tom's Cabin.</em>", "answer": "Harriet Beecher <b><u>Stowe</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Cincinnati's George Remus made his fortune in this activity, possibly inspiring the title character of <em>The Great Gatsby</em>. An urban legend stating that the Kennedy family originally made its fortune in this activity is based on the testimony of Frank Costello, one of many mobsters involved in it. For 10 points, what was this activity of smuggling alcohol during Prohibition?", "answer": "<b><u>bootlegging</u></b> or <b><u>rumrunning</u></b> [prompt on descriptive answers]  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 3 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This state was the home of the \"sage of Emporia,\" Progressive activist William Allen White. This state dropped the teaching of evolution from science classes in 1999. Earlier, this state was where \"Border Ruffians\" perpetrated the sack of Lawrence and were subject to the Pottawatomie Massacre by John Brown. For 10 points, name this state which was \"Bleeding\" in the 1850s.", "answer": "<b><u>Kansas</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The Argun and Ussuri rivers demarcate part of the border between these two countries. These two countries established their border in 1689 with the Treaty of Nerchinsk, which ended a brief conflict in the Amur River region. These two countries share a border in between Mongolia and Kazakhstan. For 10 points, name these two geographically largest countries in Asia.", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b> and <b><u>China</u></b> [order not important but do not accept or prompt if only one answer is given]", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "In this sport, the Hershey Bears have won eleven Calder Cups. In 2014, Metallurg Magnitogorsk won the Gagarin Cup as champion of a prominent European league for this sport. The top league in this sport awards the Hart Trophy to its MVP and the Conn Smythe Trophy to the best playoff performer. For 10 points, name this sport whose champion receives the Stanley Cup.", "answer": "ice <b><u>hockey</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "William Jopling wrote the standard textbook on this disease. The Greek island of Spinalonga once housed people with this disease, who were treated by Marianne Cope and \"Father Damien\" on Molokai in Hawaii. For 10 points, name this disease whose causative agent was identified in 1873 by Gerhard Hansen, and whose sufferers were once isolated into namesake \"colonies.\"", "answer": "<b><u>leprosy</u></b> [or <b><u>Hansen's Disease</u></b> until \"Hansen\" is read]", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s government organized the Congress of People\u2019s Deputies and signed the Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. He introduced economic restructuring known as \"perestroika\" (<b>pr.peh-rez-TROY-kuh</b>) and government transparency called \"glasnost\". For 10 points, name this rival of Boris Yeltsin who was the final leader of the Soviet Union.", "answer": "Mikhail <b><u>Gorbachev</u></b> [Mikhail Sergeyevich <b><u>Gorbachev</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Following this battle, Locris and Phocia (<b>pr. FOH-see-uh</b>) \"Medized\" (<b>pr. MEED-eyzd</b>). This battle ended after Ephialtes (<b>pr. eph-FYE-ull-TEEZ</b>) showed the \"goat path\" to the winning force, commanded by Xerxes (<b>pr. ZERK-seez</b>). For 10 points, name this 480 BC battle in which Leonidas (<b>pr. LEE-oh-NYE-duss</b>) led three hundred Spartans in holding a pass for three days against Persia.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Thermopylae</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man collected scrapbooks filled with pictures of Condoleeza Rice, and he once set up a tent near the United Nations where he resided with his \"Amazonian Guard.\" He was killed near Sirte (<b>pr. SUR-tay</b>) in October 2011 following his overthrow in the Arab Spring. For 10 points, identify this nemesis of Ronald Reagan who was the forty-year dictator of Libya.", "answer": "Muammar <b><u>Gadaffi</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "John Bahcall and Raymond Davis searched for these particles in the Homestake experiment. The 1956 experiment of Clyde Cowan and Frederick Reines confirmed their existence. Enrico Fermi coined the name for these particles, whose \"flavor oscillation\" was a problem of late twentieth-century physics. For 10 points, name these particles with very little mass and no charge.", "answer": "<b><u>neutrino</u></b>s [or anti<b><u>neutrino</u></b>s; or solar <b><u>neutrino</u></b>s]", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>A person by this name was the fanatically Catholic Duke of Guise (</u></b><u>pr. GHEEZ</u><b><u>) while</u></b> <b><u>another man of this name was the final king of the</u> </b> <b><u>Valois (</u></b><u>pr. val-WAH</u><b><u>) Dynasty. Another</u></b> <b><u>man of this name was originally the king of</u> (+) Navarre and said\"Paris is worth a mass\" to explain his conversion to Catholicism</b>. <b>(*) </b>For 10 points, give this name of three men who fought the last French War of Religion, including the first Bourbon king of France.", "answer": "<b><u>Henry</u></b> [or <b><u>Henri</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man died mysteriously at the Grinder's Stand inn in 1809 while journeying on the</u></b> <b><u>Natchez Trace. In 1804, he departed from St. Louis</u> (+) with another man whom he had hired for the Corps of Discovery. Along the way, he met</b> (*) Sacajawea and reached the British Oregon Territory. For 10 points, name this man who was appointed to explore western North America by Thomas Jefferson along with William Clark.", "answer": "Meriwether <b><u>Lewis</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>When this phenomenon is enacted to target negative externalities, it is known as</u></b> <b><u>\"Pigouvian\" (</u></b><u>pr. pig-OO-vee-uhn</u><b><u>). According to supply-side economics, this process produces</u></b> <b><u>similar (+)</u> revenues at the extremes, as demonstrated by the Laffer curve. A slogan in the American revolution decried the imposition of this process (*)</b> \"without representation.\" For 10 points, identify this process in which the government legally compels people to provide money.", "answer": "<b><u>tax</u></b>ation", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "<b><u>During primaries in this Presidential election year, hippies were urged to shave in the</u></b> <b><u>\"keep clean for Gene\" campaign. A ticket in this election year contained a man who</u></b> <b><u>promised to \"bomb them back into the (+)</u> Stone Age\" and was the last third-party Presidential ticket to capture multiple electoral votes. The success of George (*)</b> Wallace in this election year inspired the alleged \"Southern Strategy.\" For 10 points, name this year in which Hubert Humphrey lost to Richard Nixon.", "answer": "United States Presidential election of 19<b><u>68</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This man led a legion in support of the Colorado Party during the Uruguayan Civil War.</u></b> <b><u>He later took command of the Hunters of the Alps to fight against Austria, which challenged</u></b> <b><u>his project that included the Siege of (+)</u> Gaeta undertaken by the Expedition of the Thousand. This man allied with Count (*)</b> Cavour to achieve the Risorgimento (<b>pr. ree-SORGE-ee-MEN-toe</b>). For 10 points, name this general who led the Redshirts on a successful campaign to unify Italy.", "answer": "Giuseppe <b><u>Garibaldi</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Investigator Leonora Barry advocated for women within this organization. This</u></b> <b><u>organization was led by a \"Grand Master Workman\" and was an expansion of a</u></b> <b><u>Philadelphia-based tailors' union led by (+)</u> Uriah Stephens. The Union Pacific strike of 1884 was its high-water mark, and it eventually lost influence due to excluding (*)</b> unskilled workers and most blacks. For 10 points, name this first large trade union in the U.S., which grew under Terrence Powderley.", "answer": "<b><u>Knights of Labor</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The latest date for this facility's destruction is 642, according to the story blaming Amr ibn</u></b> <b><u>al As, though it is also believed that Theophilus ordered it (+)</u> burned in 391 or that it fell victim to the chaos of the Zenobia revolt. This building housed thousands of (*)</b> scrolls and tablets and was the jewel of a complex dedicated to the Muses by Ptolemy (<b>pr. TAH-luh-mee</b>).  For 10 points, name this center of learning in the Classical world, which was found in Egypt.", "answer": "<b><u>Library of Alexandria</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In a musical named for this dance, Judge Forestier (</u></b><u>pr. for-ess-TEER</u><b><u>) finally concludes</u></b> <b><u>that \"It's All Right With Me.\" That Cole Porter musical discusses the scandal that this</u></b> <b><u>dance, which is in 2/4 time and based on the quadrille (</u></b><u>pr. kwah-DREEL</u><b><u>), caused when it was</u></b> <b><u>introduced to (+)</u> Paris in 1858. This dance first appeared in Jacques (*)</b> Offenbach's <em>Orpheus</em> <em>in the Underworld</em>. For 10 points, name this characteristic French music hall dance involving women kicking their legs high.", "answer": "the <b><u>can-can</u></b> <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 3 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras ONLY USE IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>This man revised the pamphlet</u> </b><em><b><u>The Falsifiers of History</u> </b></em><b><u>to present his side of 1930s events,</u></b> <b><u>and he gave the \"Dizzy From Success\" speech to explain why he was modifying goals of the</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> First Five-Year Plan. This leader orchestrated the \"show trials\" of army generals and others, decimating his military before the (*)</b> Nazi invasion of his country in Operation Barbarossa. For 10 points, name this fan of gulags who was the dictator of the Soviet Union from 1924 to 1953.  ANSWER: Joseph <b><u>Stalin</u></b> [or Ioseb Besarionis Dze <b><u>Jugashvili</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}